{
   "quiz" : [
      {
         "question" : "My son, forget not my .........; but let thine heart keep my ............",
         "opta" : "love, law",
         "optb" : "law, love",
         "optc" : "law, commandments",
         "optd" : "commandment, love",
         "answer" : "law,commandments",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:1  My son, forget not my law; but let thine heart keep my commandments"
      },
      {
         "question" : "So shalt thou find favour and good understanding in the sight of ............ and ............",
         "opta" : "God, Man",
         "optb" : "Man, God",
         "optc" : "Lord, Man",
         "optd" : "God, Parent",
         "answer" : "God, Man",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:4 So shalt thou find favour and good understanding in the sight of God and man."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Trust in the ........ with all thine ...........; and lean not unto thine own ...............",
         "opta" : "Lord, might, wisdom",
         "optb" : "Lord, might, understanding",
         "optc" : "Lord, heart, understanding",
         "optd" : "Lord, power,foolishness",
         "answer" : "Lord, heart, understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:5 Trust in the Lord with all thine heart; and lean not unto thine own understanding"
      },
      {
         "question" : "In all thy ways ........... him, and he shall ...........",
         "opta" : "love, love you",
         "optb" : "acknowledge, lead you",
         "optc" : "acknowledge, baptise you",
         "optd" : "acknowledge, direct thy paths",
         "answer" : "acknowledge, direct thy paths",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:6 In all thy ways acknowledge him, and he shall direct thy paths."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Be not .......... in thine own eyes: ............ the ........., and depart from evil.",
         "opta" : "wise, fear, Lord",
         "optb" : "wise, fear, God",
         "optc" : "smart, fear, Parent",
         "optd" : "wise, fear, Jesus",
         "answer" : "wise, fear, Lord",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:7 Be not wise in thine own eyes: fear the Lord, and depart from evil."
      },
      {
         "question" : "My son, despise not the ........... of the Lord; neither be weary of his ................:",
         "opta" : "saying, words",
         "optb" : "chastening, correction",
         "optc" : "chastenings, rebuke",
         "optd" : "correction, chastening",
         "answer" : "chastening, correction",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:11  My son, despise not the chastening of the Lord; neither be weary of his correction:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "For whom the Lord loveth he ..........; even as a father the son in whom he delighteth.",
         "opta" : "correcteth",
         "optb" : "direct",
         "optc" : "care for",
         "optd" : "lead",
         "answer" : "correcteth",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:12 For whom the Lord loveth he correcteth; even as a father the son in whom he delighteth."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Happy is the man that findeth ........, and the man that getteth ..................",
         "opta" : "wife,wisdom",
         "optb" : "wisdom,knowledge",
         "optc" : "wisdom, understanding",
         "optd" : "understanding, wisdom",
         "answer" : "wisdom, understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:13 Happy is the man that findeth wisdom, and the man that getteth understanding."
      },
      {
         "question" : "The ....... shall inherit ........: but .......... shall be the promotion of .......",
         "opta" : "wise, glory, shame, fools",
         "optb" : "wise, glory, fools, wise",
         "optc" : "smart, kingdom, shame,fools",
         "optd" : "wise, glory, shame, fool",
         "answer" : "wise, glory, shame, fools",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:35 The wise shall inherit glory: but shame shall be the promotion of fools."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For the Lord shall be thy ............., and shall keep thy ........... from being taken.",
         "opta" : "shelter, foot",
         "optb" : "confidence, foots",
         "optc" : "shelter, wealth",
         "optd" : "confidence, foot",
         "answer" : "confidence, foot",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:26 For the Lord shall be thy confidence, and shall keep thy foot from being taken."
      },
      {
         "question" : "By his ................... the ........... are broken up, and the clouds drop down the dew.",
         "opta" : "knowledge, enemies",
         "optb" : "knowledge, depths",
         "optc" : "understanding, depths",
         "optd" : "knowledge, depth",
         "answer" : "knowledge, depths",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:20 By his knowledge the depths are broken up, and the clouds drop down the dew."
      },
      {
         "question" : "The Lord by ............. hath founded the ........; by ............ hath he established the ............",
         "opta" : "wisdom, earth, understanding, heavens",
         "optb" : "wisdom, world, knowledge, heavens",
         "optc" : "wisdom, earth, understanding, heaven",
         "optd" : "wisdoms, earth, understanding, heaven",
         "answer" : "wisdom, earth, understanding, heavens",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3: 19 The Lord by wisdom hath founded the earth; by understanding hath he established the heavens."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Length of days is in her ...........; and in her .......... riches and ...........",
         "opta" : "right hand, left hand, honour",
         "optb" : "left hand, right hand, honour",
         "optc" : "right hand, left hand, glory",
         "optd" : "left hand, right hand, glory",
         "answer" : "right hand, left hand, honour",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:16 Length of days is in her right hand; and in her left hand riches and honour."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Say not unto thy ............., Go, and come again, and tomorrow I will give; ............... it by thee.",
         "opta" : "love ones, when thou have",
         "optb" : "neighbours, when thou hast",
         "optc" : "friends, when thou have",
         "optd" : "neighbour, when thou hast",
         "answer" : "neighbour, when thou hast",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:28 Say not unto thy neighbour, Go, and come again, and tomorrow I will give; when thou hast it by thee."
      },
      {
         "question" : "The curse of the Lord is in the .................: but he blesseth the ............... of the just.",
         "opta" : "house of the wicked, habitation",
         "optb" : "house of the evil one, habitation",
         "optc" : "house of the wicked, generation",
         "optd" : "house of the wicked, family",
         "answer" : "house of the wicked, habitation",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:33  The curse of the Lord is in the house of the wicked: but he blesseth the habitation of the just."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Envy thou not the ......................, and choose none of his ways.",
         "opta" : "oppressor",
         "optb" : "failure",
         "optc" : "oppress",
         "optd" : "oppessors",
         "answer" : "oppressor",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3: 31 Envy thou not the oppressor, and choose none of his ways."
      },
      {
         "question" : "........ with a man without ..........., if he have done thee ............",
         "opta" : "Strive not, cause, no harm",
         "optb" : "Be happy, envy, no harm",
         "optc" : "Eat, scared, no harm",
         "optd" : "Strive not, cause, harm",
         "answer" : "Strive not, cause, no harm",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:30 Strive not with a man without cause, if he have done thee no harm."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For the froward is ........ to the Lord: but his .......... is with the .....................",
         "opta" : "abomination, secret, righteous",
         "optb" : "abomination, needs, righteous",
         "optc" : "abomination, ways, righteous",
         "optd" : "abomination, secret, Lord",
         "answer" : "abomination, secret, righteous",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 3:32 For the froward is abomination to the Lord: but his secret is with the righteous."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For I give you ........, forsake ye not my ........",
         "opta" : "good doctrine, law",
         "optb" : "good law, doctrine",
         "optc" : "good law, discipline",
         "optd" : "good doctrine, words",
         "answer" : "good doctrine, law",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:2 For I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Then he ........... , and he said to me, Take hold of my ........ with all your heart; keep my .........., and you will live.",
         "opta" : "enlight me, commands, saying",
         "optb" : "taught me, advices, commandments",
         "optc" : "taught me, words, commandments",
         "optd" : "taught me, words, commands",
         "answer" : "taught me, words, commands",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:4 Then he taught me, and he said to me, Take hold of my words with all your heart; keep my commands, and you will live."
      },
      {
         "question" : "When you ......., your steps will not be ......; when you run, you will not ........",
         "opta" : "walk, hampered, stumble",
         "optb" : "obey, move, fall",
         "optc" : "obey, hampered, stumble",
         "optd" : "walk, hampered, fall",
         "answer" : "walk, hampered, stumble",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:12 When you walk, your steps will not be hampered;\r\n    when you run, you will not stumble."
      },
      {
         "question" : "A ...... man will hear, and will increase ..........; and a man of ............ shall attain unto wise counsels:",
         "opta" : "wise, learning, understanding",
         "optb" : "wise, knowing, knowledge",
         "optc" : "wise, learning, knowledge",
         "optd" : "wise, knowledge, understanding",
         "answer" : "wise, learning, understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:5 A wise man will hear, and will increase learning; and a man of understanding shall attain unto wise counsels:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "The ........... of the Lord is the beginning of .........: but ........... despise wisdom and instruction.",
         "opta" : "fear, knowledge, fools",
         "optb" : "fear, wisdom, fool",
         "optc" : "fear, knowledge, fool",
         "optd" : "fear,wisdom, fools",
         "answer" : "fear, knowledge, fools",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:7  The fear of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge: but fools despise wisdom and instruction."
      },
      {
         "question" : "My son, hear the .......... of thy father, and .......... not the law of thy mother:",
         "opta" : "saying, shun down",
         "optb" : "saying, forsake",
         "optc" : "word, forsake",
         "optd" : "instruction, forsake",
         "answer" : "instruction, forsake",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:8  My son, hear the instruction of thy father, and forsake not the law of thy mother:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "My son, if ............ entice thee, ...... thou not.",
         "opta" : "sinners, consent",
         "optb" : "sinner, agree",
         "optc" : "evil one, consent",
         "optd" : "sinners, conset",
         "answer" : "sinners, consent",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:10  My son, if sinners entice thee, consent thou not."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Then shall they call upon me, but I will ..............; they shall ..........., but they shall not find me:",
         "opta" : "not answer, seek",
         "optb" : "answer, call upon me",
         "optc" : "not answer, seek me early",
         "optd" : "answer, seek me",
         "answer" : "not answer, seek me early",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:28  Then shall they call upon me, but I will not answer; they shall seek me early, but they shall not find me:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "For that they .......... knowledge, and did .......... the fear of the Lord:",
         "opta" : "loveth, choose",
         "optb" : " hated, choose",
         "optc" : "loveth, not choose",
         "optd" : "hated, not choose",
         "answer" : "hated, not choose",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:29  For that they hated knowledge, and did not choose the fear of the Lord:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "Therefore shall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their ...........",
         "opta" : "own devices",
         "optb" : "lust",
         "optc" : "devices",
         "optd" : "interest",
         "answer" : "own devices",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:31  Therefore shall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For the turning away of the simple shall slay them, and the ......... of fools shall ......... them.",
         "opta" : "prosperity, destroy",
         "optb" : "prosperity, saved",
         "optc" : "thought, saved",
         "optd" : "prosperity, enrich",
         "answer" : "prosperity, destroy",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:32  For the turning away of the simple shall slay them, and the prosperity of fools shall destroy them."
      },
      {
         "question" : "But whoso ......... unto me shall dwell safely, and shall be ....... from fear of evil.",
         "opta" : "hearkeneth, quiet",
         "optb" : "harken, quiet",
         "optc" : "harkeneth, protected",
         "optd" : "obey, shelter",
         "answer" : "hearkeneth, quiet",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 1:33  But whoso hearkeneth unto me shall dwell safely, and shall be quiet from fear of evil."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For the Lord giveth ......: out of his mouth cometh .......... and ...................",
         "opta" : "knowledge, wisdom, understanding",
         "optb" : "wisdom, knowledge, understanding",
         "optc" : "understanding, wisdom, knowledge",
         "optd" : "knowledge, understanding, wisdom",
         "answer" : "wisdom, knowledge, understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:6  For the Lord giveth wisdom: out of his mouth cometh knowledge and understanding."
      },
      {
         "question" : "He layeth up sound wisdom for the .......: he is a buckler to them that walk uprightly.",
         "opta" : "christian",
         "optb" : "righteous",
         "optc" : "believers",
         "optd" : "Apostles",
         "answer" : "righteous",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:7  He layeth up sound wisdom for the righteous: he is a buckler to them that walk uprightly."
      },
      {
         "question" : "When wisdom entereth into thine heart, and knowledge is pleasant unto thy ..........;",
         "opta" : "system",
         "optb" : "body",
         "optc" : "heart",
         "optd" : "soul",
         "answer" : "soul",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:10  When wisdom entereth into thine heart, and knowledge is pleasant unto thy soul;"
      },
      {
         "question" : ".............. shall preserve thee, .............. shall keep thee:",
         "opta" : "Discretion, understanding",
         "optb" : "Lord, truth",
         "optc" : "Scripture, Lord",
         "optd" : "Lord, understanding",
         "answer" : "Discretion, understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:11  Discretion shall preserve thee, understanding shall keep thee:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "To deliver thee from the way of the evil man, from the man that speaketh ...........;",
         "opta" : "froward things",
         "optb" : "truth",
         "optc" : "evil",
         "optd" : "froward",
         "answer" : "froward things",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:12  To deliver thee from the way of the evil man, from the man that speaketh froward things;"
      },
      {
         "question" : "For her house ............ unto death, and her paths unto the dead.",
         "opta" : "inclineth",
         "optb" : "lead",
         "optc" : "path",
         "optd" : "guide",
         "answer" : "inclineth",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:18  For her house inclineth unto death, and her paths unto the dead."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For the ........... shall dwell in the land, and the .......... shall remain in it.",
         "opta" : "upright, perfect",
         "optb" : "youths, christian",
         "optc" : "perfect man, upright",
         "optd" : "upright, upright",
         "answer" : "upright, perfect",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:21  For the upright shall dwell in the land, and the perfect shall remain in it."
      },
      {
         "question" : "But the ........ shall be cut off from the earth, and the .............. shall be rooted out of it.",
         "opta" : "devil, calamity",
         "optb" : "evil one, transgressors",
         "optc" : "wicked, transgressors",
         "optd" : "wicked, transgressor",
         "answer" : "wicked, transgressors",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 2:22  But the wicked shall be cut off from the earth, and the transgressors shall be rooted out of it."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For I give you .........., forsake ye not my law.",
         "opta" : "good doctrine",
         "optb" : "good saying",
         "optc" : "good scripture",
         "optd" : "sound doctrine",
         "answer" : "good doctrine",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:2  For I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law."
      },
      {
         "question" : "He taught me also, and said unto me, Let thine heart retain my words: keep my .............., and live.",
         "opta" : "commandments",
         "optb" : "saying",
         "optc" : "laws",
         "optd" : "words",
         "answer" : "commandments",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:4  He taught me also, and said unto me, Let thine heart retain my words: keep my commandments, and live."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Get ........., get .......: forget it not; neither decline from the words of my mouth.",
         "opta" : "understanding, wisdom",
         "optb" : "wisdom, understanding",
         "optc" : "knowledge, wisdom",
         "optd" : "understanding, knowledge",
         "answer" : "wisdom, understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:5  Get wisdom, get understanding: forget it not; neither decline from the words of my mouth."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Forsake her not, and she shall ............ thee: love her, and she shall keep thee.",
         "opta" : "preserve",
         "optb" : "love",
         "optc" : "protect",
         "optd" : "guide",
         "answer" : "preserve",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:6  Forsake her not, and she shall preserve thee: love her, and she shall keep thee."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Wisdom is the principal thing; therefore get wisdom: and with all thy getting get ...........",
         "opta" : "understanding",
         "optb" : "knowledge",
         "optc" : "wisdom",
         "optd" : "mischief",
         "answer" : "understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:7  Wisdom is the principal thing; therefore get wisdom: and with all thy getting get understanding."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Exalt her, and she shall promote thee: she shall bring thee to ..........., when thou dost embrace her.",
         "opta" : "honour",
         "optb" : "crown",
         "optc" : "help",
         "optd" : "shelter",
         "answer" : "honour",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:8  Exalt her, and she shall promote thee: she shall bring thee to honour, when thou dost embrace her."
      },
      {
         "question" : "She shall give to thine head an ......... of grace: a crown of .......... shall she deliver to thee.",
         "opta" : "ornament, glory ",
         "optb" : "ornament, honour",
         "optc" : "crown, glory",
         "optd" : "crown, glory",
         "answer" : "ornament, glory ",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:9 She shall give to thine head an ornament of grace: a crown of glory shall she deliver to thee."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Hear, O my son, and receive my ............; and the years of thy life shall be many.",
         "opta" : "sayings",
         "optb" : "words",
         "optc" : "saying",
         "optd" : "word",
         "answer" : "sayings",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:10  Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings; and the years of thy life shall be many."
      },
      {
         "question" : "I have taught thee in the way of ..........; I have led thee in right paths.",
         "opta" : "Lord",
         "optb" : "God",
         "optc" : "wisdom",
         "optd" : "understanding",
         "answer" : "wisdom",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:11  I have taught thee in the way of wisdom; I have led thee in right paths."
      },
      {
         "question" : "When thou goest, thy steps shall not be .........; and when thou runnest, thou shalt not .......",
         "opta" : "straitened, stumble",
         "optb" : "moved, slip",
         "optc" : "ashamed, stumble",
         "optd" : "ashamed, be disappointed",
         "answer" : "straitened, stumble",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:12  When thou goest, thy steps shall not be straitened; and when thou runnest, thou shalt not stumble."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Enter not into the ...... of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men.",
         "opta" : "path",
         "optb" : "way",
         "optc" : "gate",
         "optd" : "say",
         "answer" : "path",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:14  Enter not into the path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For they eat the bread of ........., and drink the wine of ................",
         "opta" : "wickedness, violence",
         "optb" : "rich, poor",
         "optc" : "rich, violence",
         "optd" : "violence, wickedness",
         "answer" : "wickedness, violence",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:17  For they eat the bread of wickedness, and drink the wine of violence."
      },
      {
         "question" : "But the path of the just is as the .............., that shineth more and more unto the ..... day.",
         "opta" : "shining light, perfect",
         "optb" : "light, nice",
         "optc" : "narrow way, perfect",
         "optd" : "shining light, tribulation",
         "answer" : "shining light, perfect",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:18  But the path of the just is as the shining light, that shineth more and more unto the perfect day."
      },
      {
         "question" : "The way of the .......... is as .............: they know not at what they .............",
         "opta" : "wicked, darkness, stumble",
         "optb" : "righteous, light, inherit",
         "optc" : "righteous, gold, inherit",
         "optd" : "wicked, thick darkness, stumble",
         "answer" : "wicked, darkness, stumble",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:19  The way of the wicked is as darkness: they know not at what they stumble."
      },
      {
         "question" : "My son, attend to my words; incline thine ear unto my ............",
         "opta" : "sayings",
         "optb" : "prophecies",
         "optc" : "doctrine",
         "optd" : "words",
         "answer" : "sayings",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:20  My son, attend to my words; incline thine ear unto my sayings."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Let them ............ from thine eyes; keep them in the midst of thine heart.",
         "opta" : "not depart",
         "optb" : "depart",
         "optc" : "maybe depart",
         "optd" : "depart not",
         "answer" : "not depart",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:21  Let them not depart from thine eyes; keep them in the midst of thine heart."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Keep thy heart with all ...........; for out of it are the ............ of life.",
         "opta" : "diligence, issues",
         "optb" : "dilligence, issue",
         "optc" : "dilligences, issues",
         "optd" : "dilligence, blessing",
         "answer" : "diligence, issues",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:23  Keep thy heart with all diligence; for out of it are the issues of life."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Put away from thee a ........., and perverse ..... put far from thee.",
         "opta" : "froward mouth, lips",
         "optb" : "evil thought, lip",
         "optc" : "froward saying, lip",
         "optd" : "froward mouth, do",
         "answer" : "froward mouth, lips",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 4:24  Put away from thee a froward mouth, and perverse lips put far from thee."
      },
      {
         "question" : "My son, attend unto my ........, and bow thine ear to my ...............:",
         "opta" : "wisdom, understanding",
         "optb" : "understanding, wisdom",
         "optc" : "saying, wisdom",
         "optd" : "law, wisdom",
         "answer" : "wisdom, understanding",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 5:1 My son, attend unto my wisdom, and bow thine ear to my understanding:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "For the lips of a strange woman drop as an ......., and her mouth is smoother than oil:",
         "opta" : "honeycomb",
         "optb" : "honey",
         "optc" : "honeycombs",
         "optd" : "honeys",
         "answer" : "honeycomb, ",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 5:3 For the lips of a strange woman drop as an honeycomb, and her mouth is smoother than oil:"
      },
      {
         "question" : "But her end is bitter as ........, sharp as a two-edged sword.",
         "opta" : "wormwood",
         "optb" : "bitter leave",
         "optc" : "wormwoods",
         "optd" : "bitter",
         "answer" : "wormwood",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Proverbs 5:4 But her end is bitter as wormwood, sharp as a two-edged sword."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Jesus answered and said unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man ..........., he cannot see the kingdom of God.",
         "opta" : "repent",
         "optb" : "be born again",
         "optc" : "forsake sins",
         "optd" : "born again",
         "answer" : "be born again",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:3 Jesus answered and said unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God."
      },
      {
         "question" : "Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born of .............. and of the ........., he cannot enter into the kingdom of God.",
         "opta" : "water, Spirit",
         "optb" : "water, God",
         "optc" : "water, Lord",
         "optd" : "water, Spirit of God",
         "answer" : "water, Spirit",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:5 Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God."
      },
      {
         "question" : "That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the ........... is .",
         "opta" : "Spirit, spirit",
         "optb" : "God, of God",
         "optc" : "Lord, of Lord",
         "optd" : "flesh, flesh",
         "answer" : "Spirit, spirit",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:6 That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit."
      },
      {
         "question" : "The wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, but canst not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the ......",
         "opta" : "Spirit",
         "optb" : "flesh",
         "optc" : "holy spirit",
         "optd" : "spirit of God",
         "answer" : "Spirit",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:8 The wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, but canst not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit."
      },
      {
         "question" : "If I have told you earthly things, and ye believe not, how shall ye believe, if I tell you of ...............?",
         "opta" : "heavenly things",
         "optb" : "the truth",
         "optc" : "things of the world",
         "optd" : "heavenly thing",
         "answer" : "heavenly things",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:12 If I have told you earthly things, and ye believe not, how shall ye believe, if I tell you of heavenly things?"
      },
      {
         "question" : "And ........ hath ascended up to heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven.",
         "opta" : "no man",
         "optb" : "Jesus",
         "optc" : "Lord",
         "optd" : "Jesus only",
         "answer" : "no man",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:13 And no man hath ascended up to heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have .....................",
         "opta" : "everlasting life",
         "optb" : "good life",
         "optc" : "everlasting",
         "optd" : "everlasting lifes",
         "answer" : "everlasting life",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:16 For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life."
      },
      {
         "question" : "That whosoever believeth in him should ........., but have eternal life.",
         "opta" : " not perish",
         "optb" : "perish not",
         "optc" : "perish",
         "optd" : "not perish on earth",
         "answer" : " not perish",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:15 That whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have eternal life."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For God sent not his Son into the world to ........... the world; but that the world through him might be saved.",
         "opta" : "condemn",
         "optb" : "destroy",
         "optc" : "eliminate ",
         "optd" : "condemns",
         "answer" : "condemn",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:17 For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world; but that the world through him might be saved."
      },
      {
         "question" : "He that believeth on him is not ...........: but he that believeth not is ........... already, because he hath not believed in the name of the only begotten Son of God.",
         "opta" : "condemn, condemned",
         "optb" : "condemned, condemned",
         "optc" : "condemn, condemn",
         "optd" : "condemned, condemn",
         "answer" : "condemned, condemned",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:18 He that believeth on him is not condemned: but he that believeth not is condemned already, because he hath not believed in the name of the only begotten Son of God."
      },
      {
         "question" : "And this is the ......, that light is come into the world, and men loved darkness rather than light, because their deeds were evil.",
         "opta" : "condemnation",
         "optb" : "evil saying",
         "optc" : "evil",
         "optd" : "false doctrine",
         "answer" : "condemnation",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:19 And this is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men loved darkness rather than light, because their deeds were evil."
      },
      {
         "question" : "And John also was baptizing in ......... near to Salim, because there was much water there: and they came, and were baptized.",
         "opta" : "Aenon",
         "optb" : "river jordan",
         "optc" : "jordan",
         "optd" : "judea",
         "answer" : "Aenon",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:23 And John also was baptizing in Aenon near to Salim, because there was much water there: and they came, and were baptized."
      },
      {
         "question" : "For ......... was not yet cast into prison.",
         "opta" : "John",
         "optb" : "Peter",
         "optc" : "saul",
         "optd" : "james",
         "answer" : "John",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:24 For John was not yet cast into prison."
      },
      {
         "question" : "John answered and said, A man can receive ......, except it be given him from .............",
         "opta" : "nothing, heaven",
         "optb" : "abundantly, heaven",
         "optc" : "nothing, heaven",
         "optd" : "nothing, God",
         "answer" : "nothing, heaven",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:27 John answered and said, A man can receive nothing, except it be given him from heaven."
      },
      {
         "question" : "The Father loveth the Son, and hath given ......... into his hand.",
         "opta" : "all things",
         "optb" : "all powers",
         "optc" : "dominion",
         "optd" : "powers",
         "answer" : "all things",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:35 The Father loveth the Son, and hath given all things into his hand."
      },
      {
         "question" : "He that believeth on the Son hath ............: and he that believeth not the Son shall not see life; but the ........ of God abideth on him.",
         "opta" : "life, wrath",
         "optb" : "everlasting life, wrath",
         "optc" : "everlasting, wrath",
         "optd" : "joy, wrath",
         "answer" : "everlasting life, wrath",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "John 3:36 He that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life: and he that believeth not the Son shall not see life; but the wrath of God abideth on him."
      },
      {
         "question" : "............... to God, and he will draw nigh to you. Cleanse your hands, .............; and purify your hearts, ye double minded.",
         "opta" : "Draw nigh, ye sinners",
         "optb" : "Draw, sinners",
         "optc" : "Draw nigh, sinners",
         "optd" : "Draw nigh, from evil",
         "answer" : "Draw nigh, ye sinners",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "James 4:8 Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you. Cleanse your hands, ye sinners; and purify your hearts, ye double minded."
      },
      {
         "question" : "And let us not be weary in well doing: for in due season we shall ........, if we faint not.",
         "opta" : "reap",
         "optb" : "harvest",
         "optc" : "inherit",
         "optd" : "be happy",
         "answer" : "reap",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Galatians 6:9 And let us not be weary in well doing: for in due season we shall reap, if we faint not."
      }
 ,
      {
         "question" : "Brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are spiritual, restore such an one in the spirit of meekness; considering thyself, lest thou also be tempted.",
         "opta" : "reap",
         "optb" : "harvest",
         "optc" : "inherit",
         "optd" : "be happy",
         "answer" : "reap",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : "Galatians 6:1 Brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are spiritual, restore such an one in the spirit of meekness; considering thyself, lest thou also be tempted."
      }

,
      {
         "question" : "",
         "opta" : "",
         "optb" : "",
         "optc" : "",
         "optd" : "",
         "answer" : "",
         "stage" : 1,
         "hints" : ""
      }
   ]
}
